Guide to the John Perry Miller Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Perry Miller papers
1938-1992
1961-1969
MS 1717
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
The papers consist of correspondence, clippings and writings which document John Perry Miller's career as an economist and academic administrator. The majority of these materials relate to his tenure as dean of the Yale Graduate School during the period 1961-1969.
Miller, John Perry, 1911-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Perry Miller, 1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, with the exception of sensitive information about an individual's tenure case in box 4. For this reason, it is restricted until January 1, 2040.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Personal and Correspondence, 1933-1991. II. Clippings, 1938-1983.III. Writings, 1951-1992.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of materials relating to John Perry Miller's career as an economist and academic administrator, including correspondence, clippings, and writings. The bulk of the papers date from 1961 to 1969, during Miller's tenure as the dean of the Yale Graduate School. Although the writings comprise the smallest portion of the collection, they are the most interesting. They include a number of unpublished essays, or "personal statements" by Miller on various topics related to higher education, and to graduate education in particular.
Biographical / Historical
John Perry Miller, economist and academic administrator, was born in Lynn, Massachusetts, on March 26, 1911. The son of Fred and Hilda Wagner Miller, he was educated at Harvard University, receiving his B.A. in 1932, M.A. in 1934, and Ph.D. in 1937. Dr. Miller joined the Yale faculty as visiting lecturer in economics after teaching briefly at Harvard and Princeton. He was appointed professor of economics in 1950, and served as the director of Social Sciences, one of three major faculty divisions, from 1959 to 1961. Dr. Miller was named dean of the Graduate School in 1961 and held that post until his resignation in 1969.
Dean Miller's tenure saw a number of major changes in graduate education at Yale. He established the joint M.D.-Ph.D. program, as well as the Master of Philosophy degree, the latter of which was the first of its kind in the United States. Dr. Miller also instituted a combined degree program allowing students to receive a Bachelor's and Master's degree in the same course of study. In 1962, Dean Miller served on the faculty committee that recommended admitting women as undergraduates.
Following his resignation as dean of the Graduate School, Dr. Miller was named Director of Yale's Institution for Social and Policy Studies, where he played a major role in the planning and negotiations leading to the establishment of the Yale School of Organization and Management. He resigned his directorship in 1974. During this time, he also led the Campaign for Yale, a capital fund-raising drive aimed at collecting $370 million for the university, as its chief executive officer from 1973 to 1977. Dr. Miller served as deputy provost from 1977 to 1978, then briefly resumed teaching economics before his retirement in 1981.
Dean Miller married Dorothy Marie Willard in 1942, and they had two children, Perry and Ann. He died on February 9, 1997, in Hamden, Connecticut.
Degrees, Academic; Universities and colleges -- Graduate work; Miller, John Perry, 1911-1997; Yale University. Graduate School
- Personal and Correspondence, 1938-1991, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Personal and correspondence files consist mostly of John Perry Miller's correspondence with fellow Yale faculty members. There is one folder at the beginning of the series of biographical materials, including Miller's curriculum vitae and his own biographical sketches. The remainder of the series comprises correspondence which is arranged in two sections: topical and individuals. The topical section is arranged alphabetically; the individuals section is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Biographical, 1958, 1969, 1979-1982, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Topical
      - Campaign for Yale, 1973-1978?, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Citations, 1945-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Corporation, retirement from, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Deputy provost appointment, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Draft, military, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Graduate School
        - Deanship appointment
          - 1961
            - Apr 7-13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
            - Apr 14-29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
            - May, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Deanship resignation
          - 1968 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
          - 1968 Dec-1969 Apr (Box 1, Folder 11)
          - 1969 May-Sep, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - India, general, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Presidential search, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Retirement, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Testimonials, 1961, 1969, 1973, 1979, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Yale Graduate School Association Organizing Committee, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Individuals
    - Baker-Hayes, 1945, 1951, 1959, 1961-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Joyce-Richards, 1941, 1956, 1962-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Sawyer-Taussig, 1938-1940, 1945, 1954, 1962-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Tobin, James [re:William F. Buckley, Jr.], 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Triffin-Wilde, 1961, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Williams, Frank, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified, 1939, 1966-1968, 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Clippings, 1938-1983, Series II
  Clippings consist of newspaper and magazine clippings as well as press releases, and are arranged alphabetically by topic. Many are from Yale publications.
  - Alumni day, 1965, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointments, 1953, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bernstein, Richard, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brain drain question, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1964, 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Challenge of Graduate Education" [panel discussion with John Perry Miller, George W. Pierson, G. Evelyn Hutchinson, and Kingman Brewster], Yale Alumni Magazine, 1961 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Coeducation at Yale, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Coolidge, Julian Lowell, 1938, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Course offerings, 1950, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Draft, military, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Economics, 1946-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Economics at Yale" [a series of three articles in the] Yale Daily News, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Education and city development [symposium on New Haven], 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fellowship funds, 1962, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ford Foundation grants, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Foreign students, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Freshman year, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Graduate School
    - General, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Assistant and associate deans, 1961, 1964, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Deanship appointment, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Deanship resignation, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Funding, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Graduate School Association, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - University College plan, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Harvard Graduate Society for Advanced Study and Research, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Housing [graduate student], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Humanities reforms, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Institute for Social and Policy Studies, 1970-1973, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Institute of Social Science [directorship appointment], 1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Institute of Social Science (ISS) and Institution of Social and Policy Studies (ISPS) funding, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Master of Philosophy, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Master's degrees for undergraduates, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Mory's Association, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - National Defense Education Act fellowships, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - New Haven College [appointments], 1953, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Presidential workshop ["Verbatim proceedings"], 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Problems of higher education [Yale seminar], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Provost search, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Religious Studies faculty council, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Speaking engagements, 1951, 1956-1961, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Student unrest, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Teacher training, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Tenure issues [includes clippings on the Dahl report], 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Ventures [Yale publication], 1963, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Wilson Foundation, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Yale-Berlin exchange, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Yale's 275th anniversary, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Writings, 1951-1992, Series III
  Writings are arranged alphabetically by title, and include both published and unpublished essays, as well as speeches given by Miller.
  - "Aging within the Academy", 1985 June 20 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bernstein, Richard
    General note
    See: Restricted [Open 2040 January 1] Folder 1
  - Bever, Michael B. ["Remembrances"], 1992? (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Continuity of the Educational Process: Advanced Placement in the Graduate School", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Dean's Statement on Graduate School Housing", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Economist Speaks" and "The Patron Saint of Economics at Yale..." [both concerning William F. Buckley's] God and Man at Yale, 1951, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Grades and the Graduate School", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Graduate School Alumni Fund [open letter to "Alumni and Alumnae of the Graduate School"], 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "The Graduate School and the University Community," Yale Alumni Magazine, 1964 November (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Healy, Kent T. [remarks], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - India, "General Observations on the Program", 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Let's Reform Graduate Education", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Master of Arts Degree at Yale", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Notes on the Graduate School" [memorandum for A. Whitney Griswold], 1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Presidential address at the annual meeting of the Association of Graduate Schools (in the Association of American Universities), San Francisco, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Proposals for the Reorganization of the Graduate School" [draft], 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Reforming Graduate Education", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "The Social Science Center: Yale and New Haven", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Statement to the Joint Boards of Permanent Officers of Yale College and the Graduate School", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "To the Committee for Information on the Institute for Social Science", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The University as the Sum of Many Parts", 1977 June (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Yale 1991" [edited copy of a speech delivered at the Senior Class Dinner of Morse College, May 1969], 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Restricted
  Conditions Governing Access
  This file contains sensitive information about an individual's tenure case. For this reason, it is restricted until January 1, 2040.
  - Bernstein, Richard [tenure case], 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)